Guide to the Peter Lewis Allen Collection of Safe Sex Pamphlets MSS.199
Fales Library and Special Collections
Peter Lewis Allen Collection of Safe Sex Pamphlets
1974-2007
1980-1999
Fales Library and Special Collections
Allen, Peter L., 1957-
MSS.199
2.25 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, 1 flat box, and 1 rectangular box
2 videocassettes (vhs)
Dr. Peter Lewis Allen (b. 1957) is a scholar, author, educator, and executive whose interests include culture, history, and sexuality. He has contributed to the scholarship surrounding the AIDS epidemic and the LGBT community. This collection contains pamphlets, brochures, postcards, condoms, safe sex kits, t-shirts, and two VHS tapes, all relating to sexual health issues from 1974-2007. These materials were produced and distributed in the United States, Latin America, and Europe.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dr. Peter Lewis Allen in 2007; addional materials were donated in 2009. The accession numbers related to these gifts are 2007.199 and 2009.199.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Series I. Pamphlets and Brochures; Series II: Physical Objects. Folders arranged chronologically.
Biographical Note
Dr. Peter Lewis Allen (b. 1957) is a scholar, author, educator, and executive whose interests include culture, history, and sexuality. He received a B.A. in classics and English from Haverford College, a Ph.D. in comparative literature from the University of Chicago, and an M.B.A. from the Wharton School. Allen has contributed to the scholarship surrounding the AIDS epidemic and the LGBT community including the publication, The Wages of Sin: Sex and Disease, Past and Present. After graduating from Wharton in 2000, Allen transitioned to the business world and worked for McKinsey & Company in New York, Google University in San Francisco, and Agoda.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact fales.library@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu at least two business days prior to your research visit to coordinate access.
Scope and Contents
The collection is arranged in two series. The materials in Series I include brochures, pamphlets, postcards, and magazines from the 1980s, 1990s, and early 2000s. Series II contains condoms, safe sex kits, t-shirts, and two VHS tapes. The materials focus on HIV/AIDS prevention but also include subjects such as safe sex and STD prevention, pregnancy, abstinence, drug use, teenagers and sex, menopause, and birth control. These materials were in the main published and distributed by health clinics and organizations such as Gay Men's Health Crisis and Planned Parenthood. The collection also includes several international pamphlets from Europe and Latin America.
Separated Materials
The 2009 accretion included books that were removed and added to the Fales Library collection at the time of donation.
New York (N.Y.).; AIDS International.; AIDS (Disease); Lesbians -- Sexual behavior -- United States.; Homosexuality and education -- United States -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Homosexuality and education -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; AIDS activists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc.; Brochures.; Latex (organic material); Sida Prévention.; SIDA.; Sexual intercourse -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; STDs (Diseases); Pamphlets.; Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- Germany.; Fliers (printed matter); Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- France.; Safe sex in AIDS prevention.; Homosexuality -- Comic books, strips, etc.; Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- Netherlands.; Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- Developing countries.; Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- United States.; Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Downtown Collection.; Gay liberation movement.; Sexual minorities -- Political activity; Human rights advocacy.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.. Media Dept.; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.; Gay Men's Health Crisis, Inc.. AIDS Professional Education Program
- Series I: Pamphlets, Brochures, and Related Materials
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the collection, this series contains brochures, pamphlets, postcards, and magazines from the 1980s, 1990s, and early 2000s.
  - Gay Men's Health Crisis Materials, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1980s, 1974-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1996-2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlets, Flyers, Magazines, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II: Physical Objects
  Series II contains condoms, safe sex kits, t-shirts, and two VHS tapes.
  - Prophylactics, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gay Men's Health Crisis t-Shirt, undated (Box 3)
  - Act Up Paris t-shirt, undated (Box 3)
  - Mark Whalberg Calvin Klein t-shirt, undated (Box 3)
  - Tim Miller: Stretch Marks [VHS], 1990 (Box Shared Fales 015)
  - Stop the Church [VHS], undated (Box Shared Fales 015)